Finding Aid for Johan G.R. Banér papers, 1890-1938
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Johan G.R. Banér papers 1890-1938
Banér, Johan G. R. (Johan Gustav Runeskeold), 1861-1938.
85997 Aa 2
Swedish-American author and journalist, of Ironwood, Michigan. Correspondence, manuscripts of poetry and other writings, and scrapbooks containing correspondence, newspaper clippings, and other poetry, concerning the myths of Sweden and Scandinavia and Banér's studies of Michigan Indian lore; also photograph.
3 linear feet
2 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Mrs. Burke Taylor (donor no. 4651 ) in 1970 and 1992.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Johan Gustav Runeskeold Banér was a noted Swedish-American author and folklorist who spent most of his life in Ironwood, Michigan. Born in Småland, Sweden in 1861, he immigrated to the United States in 1883, where he lived in Ashland, Wisconsin and Duluth, Minnesota.
While in Ashland, Banér began publishing Frihet, which became the major Swedish language publication in Minnesota, Wisconsin and Michigan. He continued to publish Frihet after he moved to Ironwood, which was home to a large Swedish speaking community. Banér also began to write poetic accounts of Scandinavian epics, as well as translations of Chippewa legends, myths and folklore; he wrote literally thousands of articles and poems for the nation's Swedish language press. As his influence as a publisher and writer spread, Banér corresponded with several well-known people, including Luther Burbank, Booker T. Washington, Elbert Hubbard, and Michigan governor Chase S. Osborn. He died in 1938.
The Johan G.R. Banér collection is an especially valuable resource for the study of immigrants in Michigan; it also provides examples of popular folklore during the first half of the twentieth century. The collection is divided into six series: Biographical Information, Correspondence, Manuscripts, Scrapbooks, Publications and Photographs; the material is written in both English and Swedish.
Subjects:
Authors, American--Michigan.; Banér, Johan G. R. (Johan Gustav Runeskeold), 1861-1938.; Indians of North America--Michigan.; Ironwood (Mich.); Journalists--Michigan--Ironwood.; Poetry.; Swedish Americans--Michigan.; Upper Peninsula (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Banér, Johan G. R. (Johan Gustav Runeskeold), 1861-1938.
Contributors:
Burbank, Luther, 1849-1926.; Hill, Joe, 1879-1915.; Hubbard, Elbert, 1856-1915.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915.
Genre Terms:
Scrapbooks.
- Biographical Information
  Biographical Information (1 folder; 1901-1973 and undated) contains clippings and reprints of articles about Banér which were written during his lifetime, along with a 1973 biography from The Swedish Pioneer Historical Quarterly, and notes and photographs by Ironwood historian Victor Lemmer.
  - Biographical Material 1901-1973, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1890-1939
  Correspondence (.3 linear ft. and 1 scrapbook; 1890-1939 and undated) is arranged in chronological order where possible. A "Calendar of Correspondence" at the beginning of the series provides an index to the people with whom Banér corresponded, as well as thumbnail descriptions of the letters' contents. There are letters in the collection from Luther Burbank, Joe Hill, Elbert Hubbard, Chase Osborn, and Booker T. Washington.
  - Correspondence undated, 1890-1939, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence Scrapbook 1914-1920 (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  Manuscripts (1 linear ft.; undated) are arranged by genre and language. "Essays" include prose fiction, articles and Banér's versions of Indian legends. "Poetry" runs from light rhymes written for family and friends, to book-length odes. Most of the manuscripts are drafts of material which was eventually published.
  - Essays concerning American Indian and Swedish folklore undated (Box 1)
  - Essays including some autobiographical writings undated (Box 1)
  - Essay "Verdandee and I" undated (Box 1)
  - Poems
    - Miscellaneous undated, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - "Cha-Yani' Pi' Kta" undated (Box 1)
    - "Checquamegon" undated (Box 1)
    - "Keshena" undated (Box 1)
    - "Keystones" undated (Box 1)
    - "Tecumtha" undated (Box 1)
    - "Viking Mettles" (2 versions) undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Essays
    - Miscellaneous undated, 6 folders (Box 1)
    - "Fran January Till December" undated (Box 1)
    - "Herr Slump Och Herr Jag" by Johan Fornmo undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - "Waldemar Thorstenson" undated (Box 2)
  - Poems
    - Miscellaneous undated, 10 folders (Box 2)
    - "Loke" undated (Box 2)
    - "25 Plus 25" undated (Box 2)
- Scrapbooks
  Scrapbooks (1 lin. ft. and 2 oversized volumes; 1893-1938 and undated) contain clippings about Banér, published versions of his work and a few photographs and calling cards from colleagues and friends. Most of the contents are in Swedish.
  - Clippings of poetry, articles, and personal items 1890s-1920s, 3 volumes (Box 2)
  - Clippings of poetry, articles, and personal items 1890s-1920s (Volume 1)
  - Clippings of poetry, articles, and personal items 1890s-1920s (Volume 2)
  - Clippings of poetry, articles, personal items and photographs 1924-1933 (Box 2)
  - Manuscripts of poetry and essays undated, 2 volumes scrapbook (Box 2)
  - Manuscripts of poetry and essays pasted in magazines 1912-1929, 6 copies (Box 3)
  - Miscellanea, poetry and articles 1926-1935, undated, 3 volumes scrapbook (Box 3)
  - Obituaries, condolences and photographs, 1938 (Box 3)
- Publications 1911-1936
  Publications (.25 linear ft.; 1911-1936) are the published book and pamphlet versions of Banér's creative work.
  - Svenska Roman Bladet [newspaper], 1889-1890 (Box 3)
  - Swedish Magazines containing Banér poems 1926-1927 (Box 3)
- Photographs, 1870-circa 1920s
  Photographs (3 envelopes; 1878-ca.1920s) are mainly of Banér, but also include pictures of his family and friends. Most of the latter are unidentified.
  - Banér family and friends circa 1880s-1920s (Box 3)
  - Portraits of Johan Banér 1878-circa 1920s, 2 folders (Box 3)